foreign
this is the active inference Institute
it's November 15
2022 and we're in model stream 7.1 we're
going to be discussing Pi mdp a python
package for active inference in discrete
State spaces we will all say hello then
we'll pass to Connor for a presentation
following the presentation we'll have
some discussion take a look over Pi mdp
scripts take any questions that are
coming up in the live chat so thanks to
the authors for joining today and also
to Jacob we'll just start by saying
hello so I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and I'm really excited to
learn a little bit more about pi mdp and
see how active inference gets applied
and I'll pass to jakub
hi everyone I'm yakub I'm a student in
the UK and also very excited to hear
more about parent and discuss the recent
uh developments and plans for future
development I'll pass it to Daphne
hi I'm Daphne
um I'm working here in London I've used
primary p a lot for work that I did with
Connor on my Master's thesis and also
just work that we've been doing since
then so
um I definitely like think it's a really
really great package and I'm happy that
people are gonna start using it more
excellent all right Connor thanks a lot
for joining take it away
great thank you thanks for the invite
I'm glad that uh we um arranged this
it's like a nice opportunity to go on
the live stream I've been on a few times
now so it's always nice to come back so
I don't have a slide introducing myself
so I'll just say a quick sentence just
about who I am so I'm Connor I'm a PhD
student in biology at um the plug
Institute for animal behavior and
Constance in Germany and most of my work
is about applying active inference and
kind of the Bayesian lens on cognitive
science and complex systems applying
that to Collective Behavior like
Collective animal behavior but today
I'll be talking about kind of one of my
side PhD projects which has been
developing this Prime DP package which
was very much a collaborative group
effort with a bunch of people from the
active inference Community
um
so yeah let's uh let's Dive In
see the the paper that the package has
actually been out for a while and the
paper came out earlier this year
um and it's just it I I want to begin by
emphasizing that primevp is very much a
work in progress even though we released
a paper and it's definitely like a
usable Standalone package it's there's
always a ton to keep developing and
towards the end of the presentation I'll
talk about some of those ongoing
developments which are really exciting
in my opinion and we'll really open up
the the usage
um and extendability of the package
thank you
so basically I mean this is an active
inference Institute podcast or a live
stream so I don't have to spend too much
time motivating I don't think active
inference but in in short the pi MVP
package is a python package for
simulating
um and running active inference
processes in discrete State spaces and
the discrete State Space Case is a very
well-studied case
um and very well characterized and it's
been very popular in like models of
decision making like discrete decision
making and planning and has seen a lot
of application in the neurosciences as
models of like
um discrete decision making behavior in
for instance humans or other animals
um so just I'll give a little outline of
the presentation
so first I'll just introduce the team of
uh people who have worked on primevp and
we're authors on the paper but the
actual effective team goes much larger
than that because there's a lot of
people who are who are developing or
using it and contributing in their own
ways that weren't actually co-authors on
the paper
um and then I'll discuss the motivation
for the package I'll give a brief
overview of active inference in discrete
State spaces but as I mentioned I think
this is a really nice like venue to have
this discussion about Palm DP because I
don't think I need to go too deep into
discussing what active inference is so
that'll save us some time to like get
more into the depth of pond DP
um I'll talk about the existing
approaches to simulating active
inference agents like namely in Matlab
using SPM and just kind of compare and
contrast Prime DP with SPM and and help
us understand like kind of where Prime
DB is coming from
um in terms of its origins in SPM really
so then we'll talk about some of the
features of prime DP and its General
package structure
and then we'll dive into a few usage
examples where I'll show some like
outputs of simulated agent behavior and
then the code that accompanies that just
to kind of demonstrate what the general
flow of Pi mdp looks like and then at
the end I'll just discuss some of the
future directions and ongoing
um active branches I guess of pine DP
their ongoing development efforts that I
think will make time EP super exciting
and extendable
um to all kinds of new use cases so I'm
really excited about that and now and as
Daniel was saying if at any point
someone wants to
um but in or it has questions for
clarification just feel free to let me
know and we can kind of dwell on some
points for longer
uh okay so I'll start by introducing the
team so they're the co-authors in the
paper Edition to me were Baron millage
Daphne to make us who is here today uh
Brennan Klein Carl friston Ian cousin
and Alexander chance so Carl and Ian are
my co-phd supervisors
and um Carl is the original
progenitor of the mdp or discrete State
space formulation of active inference in
Matlab
um so it's nice to kind of have his uh
stamp of approval on on our work here
and he's kind of cosine on that and then
just I I think it's important to
emphasize how critical everyone here is
to the package and it wasn't really just
I did do I guess most of the actual
software development but the early
stages of prime DP were really
conversations between me Brennan and
Alec back in 2019 or maybe even earlier
just about the need for a python package
that does active inference and I think
probably other people were having
similar conversations around that time
but it was because we all kind of came
together that we're able to to build
this thing in not too long of a time I
mean more than two years and it could
have probably been done faster if I was
working full-time on it but it was um
it was really fun to kind of watch the
progression of this and then as Daphne
said she's actually one of the
the first people who really used
um active Pi mdp in her own Master's
thesis and not only that but in a very
ambitious application which is like
multi-agent Collective Behavior having a
bunch of pine DP agents interacting with
each other to simulate the kind of
opinion Dynamics and Echo Chambers and
social networks which is really exciting
so that was really gratifying to work
with her on that and um yeah so it's
really nice also that Daphne is part of
this because it's like a very good
example of a Pioneer in the pi mdp
active inference community and then
Baron also uh me Alec and baron did a
lot of work on developing some of the
more sophisticated message passing
techniques inactive inference in in Pym
DP and uh Baron was also really critical
in helping me write the paper
um and he's just great at writing and
conceptualization and just was also used
actually primevp in some of his own work
on successor representations and active
inference which is kind of cool
um
okay so motivation
one of the biggest things which everyone
here is I'm well aware of is there's
just much more popularity and interest
in active inference these days in the
past 10 years and especially the last
five years
um so it's kind of obvious that we need
some more General user-friendly
Frameworks for actually letting people
learn about active inference first of
all from a pedagogical perspective as
well as applying it in their own
research or industrial applications or
whatever they want to actually do with
active inference
um and there's a lot especially of
interest in active inference from
certain communities not just
Neuroscience anymore but things like
machine learning data science
engineering Network science even
software development software engineers
and a lot of those interested Fields
um the most dominant uh language is
python so when a lot of times what I've
heard is when people come to learn about
active inference and they're have a
background in python or r or something
and they figure out that it's all in
Matlab they have a there's kind of a
barrier to entry because they either
don't know Matlab or they have a hard
time parsing Matlab code especially if
they're from like non-array programming
Frameworks like maybe they're a
front-end web developer who uses uh
JavaScript or something and they're not
actually familiar with like big
multi-dimensional array programming
um so that was another motivation for
making specifically a python package
that does active inference
um and then finally we because it's in
Python that means that we're now
creating an ecosystem that can talk to
other ecosystems so ideally primevp
isn't going to be just used in a script
that only uses Pi mdp it's going to be
used with other software packages some
of them having to do with artificial
intelligence or network science or all
kinds of Frameworks that are relevant
and so you can now kind of plug and play
with piondp agents and put them in
environments like open AI gym for
reinforcement learning for instance
and uh and now you can work with active
inference in diverse applications and
that's really great for python because
python by Design and by its Community
Driven development just has so many
different packages that were built very
well for some specific thing so now that
it's in Python you can kind of uh use it
with in tandem with all those other
python packages
um okay so now a brief intro to active
inference so the fundamental
Paradigm of active inference is that you
consider an agent embedded in its
environment
and unlike kind of traditional more
passive approaches to uh perception and
behavior where you kind of consider the
environment gives you information you do
some sensory motor transformation and
then you perform an action
active infants very much
um emphasizes the fact that inference or
the problem of dealing with uncertainty
characterizes both perception or what we
call like State estimation or belief
updating as well as action which is
where the active inference part comes
into play so agents are not only
updating their beliefs about the states
of the world the hidden States out there
by minimizing this um bound on a
surprise called free energy and that's
where these kind of ham holsian ideas of
perception as inference come from
but also you're minimizing surprise or
abound on surprise also to choose your
actions so inferring actions becomes
just another another sort of inference
problem so policies or sequences of
actions are considered latent variables
or hidden States and then you also do
inference about those and by casting
both sides of the perception action coin
as a example of surprise minimization
what you events are agents that kind of
display
purposeful and curious behavior and
there's very like there's nothing about
active inference that means you have to
use discrete State spaces or Pi MVP
that's just one particular type of or
class of generative models for active
inference
but um uh the the Palm DP discrete State
space generative models are really easy
to work with with active Insurance
because a lot of these quantities that
I'm showing here are very easy to
compute when you're dealing with palm
DPS or partially observed markup
decision processes so we'll get into all
the mathematics in in a little bit but
that's just a basic Paradigm of of
active inference agent and environment
Trying to minimize surprise both doing
perception and action by minimizing
surprise
um
and just for a more in-depth
mathematical review of active inference
and discrete State spaces namely using
these partially observed Markov decision
processes I would recommend reading this
paper which is excellent in the Journal
of medical Psychology by Lance Thomas
Noor Sebastian victorita and Carl
it's just a really great description
from a formal basis of how we get to the
update equations for active inference
starting from the most like formal
treatment of categorical and dirichlet
distributions
and also the pine DP paper the version
we have on archive also has a bunch of
appendices that do a lot of this similar
sort of math so I would also refer
people to that
okay so now let's get into the
generative models that form the bread
and butter of uh the the agent's brains
in Pym DP essentially so Central to
active inferences writing down a
generative model which is just a
specification of how an agent believes
its World Works how does it
its environment
um how does it believe its environment
influences itself like the Dynamics of
the world uh progress and how does that
those hidden State Dynamics also give
rise to observations that's all encoded
in what we call a generative model or a
world model some people also call
so
in Pine DP we only deal with a very
specific sort of gender of model which
are called these partially observed
Markov decision processes so these are a
classic Model of sequential decision
making and planning under uncertainty
they're not unique to active inference
people use Palm DP models for classical
reinforcement learning and all kinds of
decision-making problems
um they're called markovian Markov
decision process because the state at
the current time only depends on the
action in the state at the previous time
so that's the definition of a Markov
process they kind of have this shallow
temporal dependence
um that for instance a non-markovian
process doesn't have like a process that
has a longer term or deeper temporal
dependencies that stretch further back
in the past
um Palm DPS are often but not always
formulating discrete State space and
discrete time there's nothing about the
word palmdp that means they have to be
these multinomial or categorical
distributions but just when we talk
about Palm DPS and active influence
we're almost always talking about these
discrete ones
um that have to do with basically you
can only be in one of K discrete States
at a time and you only progress to one
of K discrete States at the next time so
everything's discrete but there's
nothing intrinsically about these Markov
decision processes that has to be
discrete I think it's just worth
mentioning that because that's a
important kind of conflation that people
often make when they see the word Palm
DP
um and the reason we decide to use this
uh discrete Palm DP generative model for
active inference is not just because of
the applications to sequential decision
making and planning but also there's
just a massive pre-existing active
inference literature since 2010 2011 on
using pom DPS as generative models for
decision making tests so all the
mathematics for doing active inference
with these models is already done so we
didn't have to invent any new math or
Theory to actually code this up because
a lot of it has already been written in
papers for like 10 years so that made
our life easier When developing it so
now um let's dive into just the main
components of these Palm DPS
uh there I'm only listing the four major
ones here but there's other components
that we can discuss if anyone's
interested but essentially this this
line at the top is a description of the
generative model in terms of a joint
distribution over hidden States
s and observations o in Into the Future
so uh the because of the markovian
nature of this generative model you can
write
um The Joint distribution with this
factorized basically product of
um priors and and likelihoods that
factorizes across time so that's why
they're those products over time in the
top but it doesn't matter understanding
the the math right now but the main
components which we'll map on to a
schematic in a second are the agents
beliefs about how the hidden States
cause observations which we encode in
something called the observation model
or the likelihood mapping often called
the a matrix or the a array so this is a
probabilistic representation of how do
hidden States at the current time affect
or give rise to observations at the
current time
second we have the transition or
Dynamics model which is another sort of
likelihood that encodes the agent's
beliefs about how hidden States at one
time relate to Hidden States at the next
time so this Maps
um this is what the agent uses to make
forward predictions about how will the
world evolve if this happens or if that
happens as well as to carry kind of
messages or empirical priors from the
past given where I was yesterday where
must I be now given my my beliefs about
how the world evolves sometimes that's
all encoded in the B array or the B
Matrix and then these final two are kind
of uh priors
the first of which is very important
which is called the C array or the C
Vector which encodes the agent's prior
beliefs about What observations it's
likely to encounter and as we said in
the beginning active inference is all
about casting both action and perception
as an inference problem
so active inference as a framework kind
of turns the classic Paradigm of reward
functions and reinforcement learning on
its head by saying instead of a reward
function just equip the agent with a
kind of optimistic belief that in the
future I will see this kind of data and
then by performing inference with
respect to a generative model that has
that prior belief in it the agent will
look like it's searching for
observations that conform with its
priors so this goes in line with this
idea that active inference is a process
of self-fulfilling prophecy the agent
believes I'm more or less likely to see
certain observations and then by doing
inference about policies with such a
bias to generative model the agent will
kind of bring itself to actually realize
its prior preferences or these Pro these
prior beliefs about observations
so that's all encoded in the C vector
and the C Vector you can basically think
of as the Bayesian translation of the
reward function and you can actually
exactly relate the entries of the C
Vector two rewards and reinforcement
learning but we won't we don't have to
get into that now but I can share papers
if anyone's interested and then finally
there's the prior over hidden States and
this is simply a the agent's belief
about what is the prior likelihood of
each hidden State at the at the first
time step of the simulation so this
isn't really a necessary thing in active
inference but oftentimes when we're
simulating agents we we use a finite
temporal Horizon with a start time and
an end time so if you have a like a
finite temporary Horizon it means that
you have to basically plug in a prior
belief about what the world looks like
at time step one and that prior belief
is encoded in this d d vector
and we can just intuitively sketch out
the the Palm DP generative model as a
Bayesian graph where nodes are connected
by edges by these arrows if they depend
on each other so these red nodes
represent the hidden States
transitioning to each other over time
um and the blue nodes the O nodes
represent the agent's beliefs about how
observations are generated from those
hidden States so that's just a graphical
representation of the Palm DP
and the a matrix encodes as we said the
agent's beliefs about how those red
nodes give rise to the blue nodes at any
time so usually we assume that this a
matrix is time invariant so they they
believe that this observation mapping
doesn't itself depend on time that's at
least that the Assumption made in most
Palm DPS
and then there's also the agents time
invariant beliefs about how the
transition dynamics of the world uh
bring states that time T minus one two
states at time t
en and then policy selection or action
comes into play in inactive inference by
Framing actions as controlled
transitions so the B Matrix does not
just say how does it how should the
world look now given how it was
yesterday but how should it look now
given how it was yesterday and the fact
that I took this action at time T minus
one so the B Matrix is not only
conditioned on past States but also on
previous actions so policies Pi come
into play as a belief or a distribution
over those actions so the actions
directly influence the Transitions and
then the transitions affect the states
so that's how kind of we think about
action in a lot of palm DP scenarios and
actions are or policies Pi are sequences
of actions or collections of actions
and then we have this critical objective
function uh called the expected free
energy that determines which actions are
more likely than others so by minimizing
expected free energy we optimize a
belief about policies and then the
expected free energy itself is a
function of your generative model your
beliefs about the world which includes
this biased prior belief about What
observations you expect yourself to see
so the kind of reward function enters
policy selection via this expected free
energy and that's why we're able to
still kind of call all of this a form of
an inference problem because we're
minimizing this expected bound on
surprise so and in doing so we kind of
infer distribution over policies which
we then sample from to actually generate
actions and change the world
and then as I said the D Vector is
basically just a prior on that initial
hidden State distribution
um
so yeah in summary to build a palmdp
active inference model
uh you have to write down or encode
these a b c's and D's and there's some
other priors too that we can talk about
like a prior over policies which is
called an e Vector but for now you can
just think of most of the heavy lifting
in active inference as consisting in
writing these things down actually
encoding what your agent believes about
the world that it exists in
um and these things in the case of these
categorical discrete distributions they
end up looking like matrices and vectors
since everything is categorical
distributions you you're not dealing
with continuous infinite dimensional
spaces you're dealing with things that
have a discrete number of entries like a
four by four Matrix or five by five
Matrix
uh yeah I think before we yeah so the
next part I'm going to talk about like
the Matlab python
um dialectic before we move on to that
though should we maybe pause if there's
any questions
foreign yeah great thank you
Daphne or Jakob do you want to provide
any thoughts or reflections
there's one thing that I've always been
a little bit confused about which might
be nice to resolve now which is in that
parameterization of the prior
preferences
can you explain like why exactly it is
that when you initialize them you just
do them with like
um integers greater than 1 are greater
than or equal to one but then
you like soft maximum later on when you
actually using an inference like why do
we not Define our preference of those
probabilities
yeah that's a good that's a good um
point and a good thing to mention so
in usually in both the Matlab and the
python implementation so when building
Pi mdp we made the decision to to do the
same thing when you're encoding that c
Vector instead of encoding it as
probabilities which It ultimately should
be what you really write down is the log
of the C Vector so you write it down in
terms of relative log probabilities
and the reason that's potentially a more
um
more intuitive parameterization rather
than writing it down directly in terms
of probabilities is because the log of
the probability is more like the actual
reward so if we go back to this
generative model
the expected free energy being a free
energy is actually
um
and then a free energy is sort of a kind
of KL Divergence it's encoded in terms
of bits which is naturally in a
logarithmic space
so if you're writing down like a prior
in terms of in in log space you know
kind of if I change the number of log
units in my prior preferences I have it
it's a it's more linearly related to the
change in the expected free energy for a
policy that leads to that observation
whereas if you're writing on the priors
in terms of a probability space that the
ex the resulting change in the expected
free energy from changing something in
probability space is not going to be
um linear it's going to be a non-linear
change
so if we think of rewards as log
probabilities
something that's like one extra log unit
or one natural log one Nat or one bit
more valuable than another thing that
will actually reflect itself in terms of
the expected free energy difference
between seeing Thing One versus thing
two whereas if we encode those two
things in terms of probabilities that
expected free energy difference won't be
as intuitive simply because it won't be
linear
um so that's like a quick reason for why
we decide to encode things in log space
but there's nothing mathematically
necessary by any means you could easily
just
uh write the priors directly in terms of
probabilities it's more of a it's like a
it's just a way to make it more reward
like really
yeah that makes a lot of sense thanks
thanks Jacob
yeah um I'm wondering
is there
um heart requirement on the amb matrices
or tensors to be actually encoded as
categorical matrices or because thinking
about like the function of the a matrix
and the way the agent uses it to infer
its hidden state from an observation I'm
thinking whether
would be possible to encode High
dimensional State spaces in something
like a neural network that can
approximate uh these probabilistic
representations as well uh and learn the
represent the kind of the relationship
between observations and hidden States
um
yeah definitely Yeah so basically
sorry there might be a like but yeah
basically whether you think that would
be possible and because I I feel like
the python implementation which I'm sure
you'll get into the advantages of python
over Matlab uh
also affords the interoperability with
other libraries and within data science
totally yeah that's a good great point
so I kind of mentioned towards the
beginning when we talked about Palm DPS
there's nothing about Palm DPS that
means all these things have to be
matrices the main thing that defines
upon EP is that it's partially
observable so that the the agent only
gets to see the blue nodes and that it's
a markovian process so that there's like
a temporal shallowness in the memory of
the Hidden States but you could replace
a and b with any kind of parameterized
it has to be a proper likelihood
function so it has to be have that like
um proper the properties of being a
likelihood there's nothing that means
that it can't be a multivariate gaussian
or koshy distribution or Bernoulli
distribution or uh yeah any kind of
exponential family or some like um
parameterized neural network
like that people use oftentimes in in
reinforcement learning like they'll
parameterize a Dynamics model just with
a a bunch of neural networks that say
take time State at time T and move them
to State at time t plus one the reason
there's difficulties with that is simply
because it's unclear
how to compute things like the expected
free energy once you start moving into
these
um not as nicely behaved distributions
so a lot of the reason that this
framework was developed in the discrete
categorical State version is not only
because for modeling low dimensional
tasks like someone playing a slot
machine or deciding to go left or right
in a in a y maze it's easy to use these
discrete distributions to kind of give a
good description of that behavior that's
one thing but also is literally a
mathematical tractability reason there
aren't always closed form solutions for
the expected free energy
depending on what those those
distributions look like so there's some
work on doing this for instance Magnus
cudall has a paper in entropy where they
compute the expected free energy in
linear dynamical systems basically where
all these A's and B's are represented by
gaussians so they they call this like a
linear controllable dynamical system
and they also have to make some
assumptions about how the actions affect
the B Matrix which really isn't a matrix
anymore it's more like a continuous
gaussian and and they find that the
normal terms you get with the expected
free energy like the Information Gain
those a lot of the interesting things
that we get with when we use categorical
distributions those terms actually
disappear when we use gaussian so you
actually don't get the nice like
Information Gain seeking or information
seeking terms that you would normally
get by using categoricals but there's
other ways to get around that like if
you use neural networks you can still
use things like sampling approaches to
compute expected free Energies
um where you basically like sample a
bunch of possible trajectories and then
you can use the samples like kind of
Monte Carlo style to compute expected
free energies and a lot of the groups
that have done
um like scaling active inference to deep
neural networks they've used that kind
of approach so like Alec chances paper
Scout scaling active inference does
stuff like that a lot of the stuff out
of like Tim verbalance group
um I don't want to leave anyone I think
like in nor has done obviously a lot of
North Vegeta has done a lot of active
inference with deep neural networks as a
virus found us like a lot of these
people were actually trying to apply
active inference to keep neural Nets
they have to basically come up with ways
to compute that expected free energy
that are different than the way it's
done in pi MVP because in Pine BP you
can exactly compute that expected free
energy which ends up just being a bunch
of Matrix Vector products and then a
summation
so it just becomes more difficult when
you use more complex distributions but
it's by no means
um
impossible you just have to you have to
come up with some kind of approximation
but there are ways I think you can get
around that which involve what I call
what people have been calling Hybrid
models where you might have deep neural
networks that feed into a palm DP at
like some higher layer and then the
impound DP space like a discrete
categorical space you can still compute
expected free energies and free energies
but you can still take advantage of at
lower levels like high dimensional
neural networks to project your data
into this low dimensional space so you
do all the efe active inference in this
lower dimensional Palm DP space where
everything's exact but you can still
take advantage of the nice
dimensionality reduction and feature
extraction properties of neural networks
to first like pre-process the
observations so that's something I'll
talk about at the end because we've made
some progress on the first steps towards
making that possible which involves
basically making all of Pi mdp Auto
differentiable so you can like train
neural networks that are attached to
pump the prime T models
yeah it's a great question though
awesome I see this as like the body plan
of generative models and maybe what's it
like today is an antenna tomorrow or
delay it gets longer or thicker there's
a lot of different ways to swap out and
compose different parts of the model so
thanks carry on
cool yeah
um
so yeah now let's talk a little bit
about the traditional software for
active inference research which I'm sure
everyone on the call right now is
familiar with the original way it was
done was basically uh Carl friston and a
few others wrote a bunch of Matlab
scripts part of the SPM package
just originally go out for like
neuroimaging data analysis and
statistical testing
and there's a sub package called Dem or
dynamical expectation maximization which
is used for not only active inference
including continuous active inference
but also just like generalized filtering
and and fitting non-linear State space
models from empirical data So within
that we have all the this kind of
discrete active inference toolbox most
of the functions of which are prefixed
by SPM underscore Mt mdp so the main
function that basically does everything
that Pine MVP does for the most part is
is containing one function called SPM
mdp vbx and kind of in in a
tongue-in-cheek way we often joked
around that Pine DP is just a package
that implements that one function
because that one function essentially
does active inference and learning and
all the message passing just in in one
call which in many ways is very nice
because you just have to pass in a mdp
to it and then it in a kind of Black Box
way gives you all the belief updating
and history of actions and everything
that that you need
um there are despite its elegance and
it's like usefulness and how robust it
actually is because you can pass in any
agent with any generative model and
it'll pretty much work
the issue is because it's just a single
function it's not very modular so it's
very hard to flexibly compose different
subcomputations of an active inference
process so if you want to do some
bespoke
active inference application where like
oh um before I in and do hidden State
inference I want to update the
parameters of the a matrix and I want to
do it in this particular way it's very
hard to do that in SPM mdp vbx so what
often I see happening and I did this
myself in my Master's researches I end
up having like five different versions
of this function that have some little
like specialist prefix for the the
specific thing that I was doing and then
that just ends up being like uh kind of
not not efficient because you're
creating a bunch of boilerplate code
then you have one function that does the
particular little version of active
inference that you want to explore in
your project so just by modularizing
this one function even within Matlab you
could do this you would uh basically
make the thing a lot more flexible and
save a lot of copying and pasting of
code
um another issue is that inference and
policy selection are fixed so you can't
kind of compare and contrast different
message passing approaches and action
selection routines so there's just one
way it's done in SPM vbx which is called
marginal message passing
um and so it's hard to like compare that
like what if you change the message
passing algorithm whereas in uh Pi MVP
we have it right now two message passing
algorithms that you can kind of side by
side compare I mean we hope to add more
in the future which is very easy because
it's just a modular thing and then
because of what we were talking about in
the beginning with it just by virtue of
this being in Matlab it's harder to
synthesize with other Frameworks like in
reinforcement learning open AI gym and
uh deep neural networks like
intensorflow flow or Pi torture Jacks so
just the fact that it's in Matlab um
already limited of course people have
found ways to do like cross language
cross-platform
um code like moving from Julia to Matlab
to Python and back but it's just a lot a
lot more heavy lifting involved in that
and then I'll just lay out some um kind
of pros and cons of Matlab and python so
one of the things I do like about Matlab
is it's very easy to get started with
array programming has a nice editor
there's a lot of use and history and
computational Neuroscience like even
when I gave this tutorial at a course on
computational Psychiatry this past year
I think the majority of the tutorials
were still using Matlab so there's still
a good reason to use Matlab just because
of the history and the number of
packages that are well suited for doing
neuroscience and psychophysics stuff so
there's that Advantage just kind of like
a almost momentum or a legacy advantage
but of course there's issues like as
proprietary I think that's the biggest
one you need to pay
um One Way or Another to to use Matlab
and there's not as much Community Driven
development I mean there is some like
the file exchange but it's not the same
level as something like Python and then
python kind of can compete with Matlab
because it has array programming in the
form of numpy of course it's open source
it's been
um widespread adopted across tons of
fields not just academic ones but lots
of commercial application and there's a
lot of community give driven development
in the form of packages like Pi VP
um but one disadvantage is for me at
least it wasn't as easy to get started
with Matlab
um as it was with Matlab because you'll
often have to like install a bunch of
things and learn about virtual
environments and you have to like learn
about a lot of more programming stuff
before getting started with using python
so I think that is one reason that
Matlab is actually still useful as a
pedagogical tool like the the time
between getting Matlab and actually
doing programming is is pretty short
which is nice
um so yeah the package is called uh it's
within this infra actively GitHub
organization it's called Pi MVP and you
can just pip install it like in a
virtual environment or just in your base
installation of python
and then once you have a piondp
installed you can kind of uh import and
use in a flexible modular way all the
different sub packages or sub modules
like the agent module which basically
just implements the agent class and then
there's different modules like inference
and control and learning that are
independent of actually an active
inference agent and you can just use
them to do message passing for hidden
State inference or to compute expected
free Energies
on possible policies or to compute
updates to parameters so all those
things can be composed and flexibly kind
of you can make kind of Frankenstein
active inference agents by composing all
these things in in the bespoke way that
you desire
and a lot of it um the main workflow of
pione P comes down to specifying the
generative model and the forms of these
discrete arrays and then plugging them
into the brain of the agent and
instantiating an agent so that is pretty
much encapsulated by these two lines at
the bottom import the agent from Pine BP
and then you just build one by plugging
in the ABCs and D's and then you have
this agent object that you can use to do
hidden State inference through methods
like in first States
infer policies which is the agent
internally computes the expected free
energy of its policies and then you
finally can sample actions so these
three lines are the the kind of the main
players of any active inference Loop
State inference policy inference and
then action selection and you just kind
of tie those in a loop over time
um to to instantiate an active inference
process and the the kind of um the
circularity of the action perception
Loop comes into play with the inputs to
the agent which are its observations and
the outputs of its action selection
where charts are its actions and of
course you need to use the Last Action
to then get a new observation and that
you you do by plugging the action into
some environment this is also in the
active inference literature often
referred to as the generative process so
the actual world out there that
generates your data so this is the kind
of classic action perception group
you'll see enacted any active inference
agent and this is also not even unique
to active inference this is just how
reinforcement learning problems are
generically framed so like open AI Jam
uses a very similar
um control flow we're kind of like
um yeah sensory motor Loop
so yeah here's an example of just um
doing that like import the agent set up
the generative model and that's the
hardest part so I kind of conveniently
put ellipses after the dot dot but
that's actually where most of the code
is going to happen is building the
generative model build the agent you
build some environment which you can
either import as a one of the stored Pi
mdp environments or you could get it
from open AI gym or you could just
create your own environment so these
this would be your code that actually
describes how the world works out there
the world that the agent is interacting
with and then you can Implement a Time
step of active inference with those few
lines of code right there and that would
all be kind of those last lines like 8
through 15 those would kind of be
wrapped Within
a loop over time
um yeah this is just more examples of
like this would be a quick way to in
this example we're not even running
active inference but we're just using
one of the message passing algorithms
from the Algos sub module to do hidden
State inference so in this case I just
created a random a matrix I created a
random observation and I gave and I made
up a random prior and then I can just do
one like fictive update of what an agent
might be doing during hidden State
inference and optimize Qs or the beliefs
about hidden States so this is an
example of how you could actually use
Pond DP to just do generic inference on
hidden Markov models you don't even need
to use it within an active inference
Loop you could just use it to do uh like
statistical inference on a hidden Markov
model with the particular algorithms
that we've provided
and then of course one of the advantages
I talked about over the SPM is that you
can create customized active inference
processes there's a lot of like extra
arguments to the agent class where you
can kind of turn on and off different
parts of the reward function or the
expected free energy for an agent so for
instance in this agent the agent does
not incorporate uh expected utility
which is the kind of reward
C Vector driven component of action
selection but the agent does use State
info gain and parameter information game
which are two other components of the
expected free energy so there's a lot of
ways that you can kind of create a
bespoke active inference agent that
doesn't that will behave in different
ways depending on these kind of uh
keyword arguments that you provide
um
yeah here are just more examples like in
this case we're using active inference
agent just to do hidden State inference
and no actions at all so the agent is
just inferring hidden States it's
updating its beliefs about the a matrix
and it's updating its beliefs about the
D vector or the initial hidden state
and so you can you know just flexibly
put together all these lines and create
an agent that does whatever you want
doesn't even need to be acting in the
world technically
okay so now I'm going to show a few
examples of pine DP in action
um so this is one that's a a classic
active inference paper it's one of my
favorite papers it was um I think it's
called scene construction and active
inference where it's describing a task
where an agent has to and this was used
to actually model human data in a
psychophysics test an agent has to gaze
contingently uncover
two out of four quadrants that that have
particular images in them
um and there's four quadrants total and
two of them have uh the images of
interest in them and if the two images
in this case are a bird and a cat image
and that's an example of a flea scene so
the Asian basically or the human has to
categorize the latent scene which is
simply defined by the combination of two
images in order and then categorize the
scene so it's basically a categorization
categorization task but the agent needs
to gaze contingently uncover a sequence
of cues before it knows what that
category is or what that scene is so it
combines the epistemic components that
we all know and love about active
inference trying to uncover the hidden
state of the World by actively sampling
it so in this case they're sampling the
World by moving their eyes to different
quadrants to uncover what's what's
behind them and then actually choosing
what the the true category is based on
what it learned about the world and
that's where it's trying to maximize
utility because there's some reward
associated with categorizing correctly
so this is an example of that which was
originally done in Matlab and I just
re-implemented in pi mdp
and this is another example where now
the the scene is
um the feed scene so the the cues are in
the lower two quadrants in this example
so the agent has to look around the
different quadrants it finally sees that
there's okay there's a bird in the lower
right seeds in the lower left so this
must be the feed scene
um and just uh to show an example of
what does that actually look like in
active inference like what does the code
look like for that so the first thing
you would do for this one is you would
set up your agent which again you just
throw in the a b c's and D's in this
case I used a particular message passing
algorithm called marginal message
passing which is the same one used in
Matlab you set up a policy depth and an
inference Horizon which is kind of like
a memory like how much of the past
observations you take into account
and then you set up a environment this
is like the external world
that the agent will be interacting with
in this case I'm calling it The Scene
construction environment which just
tells me once the agent moves its eyes
to a certain place how does that
actually then determine what the agent
sees next which will be you know
whatever is behind the quadrant that it
decided to look at so those are the main
two things those are the two sides of
the action perception Loop the agent and
the environment
and then what it's often common to do is
to get in an initial initial observation
by resetting the environment which is a
convention borrowed from openai gym you
basically do environment dot reset it's
like a method of the environment that
spits out the initial observations and
then it's often useful in these things
to create like lists or dictionaries
that have a mapping between the
observation indices which are like
integers between zero and however many
observations there are and then what
those actually correspond to
semantically so this is just a very
common way to like because all the Palm
DP and the environment will be spitting
out are like ones in twos and zeros and
all these like discrete indices but it's
useful to have these lists that you can
use to kind of semantically map
particular indices to
um things that are meaningful like
seeing the bird image or choosing
um the category one versus category two
and then once you've done that you just
write a loop over time where you're
basically performing active inference
which consists in Hidden State
estimation and policy inference
you uh sample an action
which then gets fed back into the
environment to produce another
observation and then that happens over
time so that's the whole action
perception of
so this is
um yeah so that's
it's deceptively simple how like short
it looks but I'm kind of glossing over
something that I'll talk about later
which is I mentioned earlier which is as
easy as this looks the hardest part is
actually done way before any of this
happens which is writing down the a b
c's and D's that's by far the most time
intensive and like complex part of
active inference is actually writing
down the generative model once you have
the generative model written down then
the rest basically is like clockwork you
just have to link the agent to the
environment and then just run like five
or six lines just to actually implement
the thing but the hardest part is
writing down those a b c's and D's in
the beginning
um I'll show another example which I
kind of
uh call teammates on steroids so in the
classic teamaze task
um that I forgot what the original paper
was but it's something that's been very
popular in the active inference
literature for a while
uh that I think Carl came up with maybe
in 2015 or earlier even is you have an
agent a mouse that has to visit two
potential sources of either reward or
punishment in its environment and it
doesn't know which arm of this teammate
contains the reward so it has to visit a
cue first before it knows which arm has
the reward and which one has either no
reward or like a shock like a negative
stimulus in this one I just kind of
spatially extended the teammates so the
agent has to now visit a sequence of
cues Each of which reveals the location
of the next cube in order to figure out
the final cue which is just the location
of the cheese versus the shock
so this is another example where the
agent first goes to q1 then it knows
where Q2 is and then it knows where the
cheese is so I call this epistemic
chaining because the agent doesn't
actually have to plan its its root all
the way to the final uh location of the
cheese all it has to do is get to the
next q which then reveals where the next
cue is which finally reveals where the
hidden location of the
reward is so you're kind of using
epistemic value or curiosity to allow an
otherwise temporally shallow animal to
plan its way to
um a distal reward or something that's
that it can't plan to get to
um our priori
and again this is just an example of
what that would look like in Pine DP
where it basically looks exactly the
same it's just that the environment and
the generative model are different but
the general flow of the code is always
has this this kind of classic pipeline
um and okay so now I'll get to the kind
of the most important part and I think
the biggest source of confusion
um with active inference is that the
hardest part is the generative model
it's all the
um complexity comes into encoding the
agent's beliefs about the world so how
do I write down the a B's and C's and
D's
in in paradigms like deep neural
networks or like unsupervised learning
you don't have to write down the modern
the the
neural network learns the model by just
observing loads and loads of data so
it's less sample efficient but you don't
have to encode as much to begin with so
this is kind of the
kind of coincides with a larger divide
between model 3 and model based
approaches with deeper neural networks
you're you're effectively
issuing the sample the statistical
complexity of having to write down the
model by just sticking together a bunch
of non-linear function approximators and
then just learning the beliefs that the
agent has about the World by just
bombarding it with data the same thing
goes for deep reinforcement learning
like DQ learning in active inference the
agents are much more sample efficient in
the sense that they don't need to train
on like billions of data vectors but on
the other hand there's more investment
on your end as the modeler because you
have to write down explicitly what the
agent's beliefs about the world are you
don't just equip it with something as
generic as a convolutional layer and
some reviews and stuff and then let it
learn you actually have to hand code
that so I think this is one of the
biggest differences between model based
reinforcement learning where you
actually encode a Bayesian General
generative model of the world and kind
of more model free or data-driven
approaches but there is it's not such a
dichotomy there are ways to kind of
combine the two
but just to kind of show
um that very specifically for instance
in this scene construction demo that I I
showed like a few slides ago if you just
look in terms of sheer lines of code
which one took more code you can kind of
use the the amount of lines of code as a
proxy for statistical complexity or how
much information is contained so the
simulation itself running the active
inference Loop was like 15 lines of code
just like and and they and that code
itself is already very generic and not
specific to the scene construction demo
writing the generative model itself
that's where all the heavy lifting is
done that's where all the information
that's specific to that task gets
encoded so for instance I just look at
how I created the a matrix the beliefs
about the observation mapping for the
scene construction demo that already is
like way more code than just running the
entire active inference simulation so
just like by the the sheer amount of
code you can already tell oh yeah
there's a lot of assumptions and and
information that's being baked into the
generative model and that's where most
of the heavy lifting of active inference
actually comes from
um yeah so I just think it's important
to remark on that because that's like a
really key thing that I think anyone who
wants to start working with active
inference models in in discrete State
spaces should kind of wrap their head
around is that the the model does most
of the work for you the expected free
energy yes is a very interesting
objective function that has many
advantages but most of the power of
active inference comes into writing down
what your agent's beliefs about the
world are and then once you have that
then all the rest kind of just does does
the work for you because the pi NDB code
is very generic what's not generic is
how you encode the beliefs about the
world
um okay so now I'm kind of finishing up
maybe we should dwell just on that bit
for a second does anyone have thoughts
or comments or questions about this
if not I can just proceed and finish off
Daphne or Jacob or I'll ask one
I don't have any questions
all right well you've emphasized the
specification of the agent's generative
model
and how about the other side of the coin
how do we specify a generative process
how do we specify the environment for
the agents
that's a really good question yeah
basically everything I said about the
generative model
um kind of applies to the generative
process as well
except the agent's interesting Behavior
yeah I mean you can you could think of
the generative process as driving a lot
of that too
I I guess the bottleneck is the
generative model because if you create a
really complex generative process so a
really complex environment that has all
kinds of fancy non-linear Dynamics but
the agent's model of the world is super
super simple so it just believes that
there's you know a light switch that's
either on or off
then the possible Behavior you can get
from such a simple agent is is limited
by the complexity of its generative
model so a very complex generative a
very simple generative model will still
not show very interesting Behavior
even if it's embedded in a complex
generative process but the most rich
Dynamics will obviously happen when you
have both a complex generative process
and a complex generative model so all
the work in um in building the
generative model which I would say is
the first line up here can also be
matched by a lot of work in generating
the the generative process as well which
in this case is this epistemic grid
World environment which is just a set of
rules that says when the agent is in the
queue location show them the queue
identity like this one is relatively
simple
but one interesting thing to think about
and I'm sure like you Daniel have
thought about this when it comes to
um you know your work on active
inference and and Collective behavior is
the interesting thing about multi-agent
Behavior is in that case the generative
process are the actions of other agents
so the generative process my generative
process are actually the outputs of
another active inference agent so that's
one of the most complicated things in
what Daphne and I had to Grapple with
when we're doing the and and Mao as well
Mao was the first author of the
epistemic communities work this like
social network Echo chamber stuff in
that context the generative process is a
little bit more difficult because the
the process itself is consisting of
other active inference agents that are
also acting so the control flow of that
code will look a little bit different
where you're going to have to Loop over
all agents get actions from them and
then use those actions to parametrize
the observations for all the other
agents I mean that's just a generic
statement about multi-agent simulations
in general but it's uh it's particularly
interesting when you think about
agents trying to model other agents
because almost necessarily every active
inference agent will have an
impoverished model of how the world
works when the the way the world works
is a bunch of interacting active
inference agents so you're going to have
to kind of necessarily equip each agent
with a more simplified generative model
unless you want them to all have like
infinite recursion depth and be able to
simulate in their own generative model
the generative models of every other
agent so yeah that's uh that I mean that
was kind of a tangent about the
multi-agent case but I think it's just
an interesting
um interesting complex to think about
the the tension between the the
generative model complexity and the
generative process complexity and how
they kind of mutually constrain the
behavior of each other
um okay shall I just proceed uh so yeah
the last two slides I think is the kind
of exciting stuff so here are a list of
things that we'd like to do with prime
DP in the future
um I'll just go through them and then
I'll dwell on a few that I think are the
most important so one is fitting Pine DP
models to empirical data so I've
interacted a lot with people from the
computational Psychiatry Community who
are interested in actually creating
models of behavior often human behavior
um that are their Palm DP active
inference models and one of the biggest
I think limitations of pine DP right now
is that people can't use pi mdp to infer
the active inference parameters of like
a human subject that's performing some
task that's what you can do in SPM right
now but unfortunately you can't do that
in Pion VP so this is like really high
in the priorities list and I think this
is what will help primary P actually
become competitive to SPM for the
communities that are interested in
fitting Pi mdp models to data so these
are like kind of more empirical
scientific disciplines like
computational psychiatry
um other things is I think we need a
better interfaces for actually
generating and constructing generative
models right now all that code involved
in Building A and B matrices that really
becomes the bottleneck for anyone trying
to do active inference and in large part
because constructing those arrays for
complex generous models can be a real
headache you have to do all this weird
multi-dimensional indexing because like
if you have like a bunch of different
interacting variables in the world you
have to create massive multi-dimensional
arrays that have different numbers of
extra Dimensions that correspond to all
these possible contingencies in the
world it kind of becomes a massive
lookup table that you have to encode all
the relationships between variables and
so I think there might be this is an
ambitious project but there might be
ways to actually create kind of uis like
user interfaces that help people build
generative models by like asking them a
sequence of questions for instance do
you want this variable to affect that
variable and then depending on their
answer you can kind of
um pre-parameterize part of the a matrix
or something and then the actual
structure of the a matrix sketch window
down to a sequence of kind of yes no
questions about the different
contingencies in the world
another thing is interfacing with openai
gym which we kind of already have done
like there's a few examples where we've
done this I haven't put these on the
on the infra actively on GitHub yet but
this is something that's an open
this is like a very obvious and easy
thing to do because like we wrote our
environment class as if it was based as
if it was a gym environment anyway so
once you do that it'll open up to
comparing active inference agents to all
kinds of reinforcement learning
algorithms
on hierarchical models is a big one so
um basically allowing you to stack
hierarchically active inference agents
within each other so like yeah there's a
lot of temporal depth that you can get
out by stacking active inference agents
into hierarchical things so like one
time scale of inference and planning is
happening at a slower one slower than a
a sub faster time scale
we need more demos that demonstrate
parameter learning so you can do
updating of a b and d arrays I don't
think you can update C so far and I know
this is something Daniel you mentioned
to me which is uh people in your in the
active inference Institute are generally
interested in
um updating the beliefs about the
generative model parameters basically
and then there's things like
sophisticated inference which is kind of
a more recent version of planning under
active inference
that's kind of interesting and has some
computational benefits to it and then
hand in hand with sophisticated
inference goes this thing that people
have developed have had to deal with in
deep reinforcement learning for a while
which is how do you tame combinatory
explosive policy spaces so when you're
doing deep planning over time uh the
number of policies is exponential in the
number of time steps that you plan in so
that's there's various techniques for
dealing with that like Monte Carlo tree
search which I think some people like
teofio Champions and others have already
tried to start implementing their own
implementations of palm DPS for
um and so along these lines I want to
just point out that we're actually very
close to getting this working now so
fitting Pi mdp models to empirical data
so there's a a branch that um Dimitri
markovic and I have been working on
called the agent Jax Branch we've
basically written a back end for pione p
and Jax which not only lets us use a
bunch of statistical probabilistic
inference techniques from like numpyro
to invert or infer the parameters of Pi
mdp Agents from like data for instance
compute uh collected from Human
participants but the fact that it's also
back-ended in Jacks means that Pi mdp is
now fully auto differentiable
so it means you could stack a deep
neural network layer onto the like
before the a matrix layer of a pi VP
agent and then you could use something
like the variational free energy or any
other objective functions to
automatically train the parameters of a
neural network that's linked to a pi VP
agent so this I think just
re-implementing it in back ends like Pi
torch and Jacks is like a huge benefit
because this will really allow you to
extend pione P to much more High
dimensional State Spaces by linking up
deep neural networks to various
components of the agent's body as you
were describing it Daniel
um and so we originally did this just to
allow you to do fitting of empirical
data but it comes with the side benefit
of allowing you to differentiate and
pass like back propagate gradients that
you would use for updating deep learning
models which is I think really exciting
so that's like almost done I mean yeah
like we're very close to putting up a
notebook that actually does that if you
look in the agent Jack's Branch now it's
not very organized but that that stuff
is now there and implemented
another thing is nor Sajid and I have
actually implemented some of the
environments from her paper active
inference demystified compared and we've
actually done that with pi MVP in openai
gym like in the frozen lake environment
is a popular one for simulating B Matrix
learning
um so that's something that's also just
like we we've done that and uh we need
to like upload that or I don't know
write a short paper do something with
that because so there's a lot of like
these different tendrils that have been
explored it's just a matter of pushing
forward and actually putting them up on
the pine BP repo
um yeah and then these other things I
would like to find time to do but I just
haven't but I mean as I kind of said in
the beginning this was very much a
collaborative effort so I don't also
want to be
um necessarily the one who's like doing
all of this because I think it also is
healthier for the development of the
package if different people are kind of
taking the lead on different things and
developing it in their own way so that's
something I also just generally like to
encourage is for all kinds of interested
people to get involved in the
development
and I don't think Brennan is here uh but
Brennan Klein also who's a
post-doc
um and research scientists at
Northeastern University at the network
Science Institute he started these Pi
mdp fellowships so he got funding from
Northeastern I think also the Templeton
Foundation to fund people to work on
Pine MVP development or prime DP
adjacent projects I think the first
round of applications is over but it
would just be a this is a good
opportunity to advertise that I think
there's going to be another cohort in
the summer so this is a kind of
seemingly ongoing source of funding so
it's just nice to see that other people
are kind of trying to push Pine VP in
their own directions so that's just an
encouraging development that I want to
keep everyone appraised of
um oh yeah and then I'll just end by
um
patient on the read the docs website
which is really nice for creating Auto
documentation and so we have a bunch of
demos up there we have different
tutorials
um we have another a new demo that's not
listed here which is about just
calculating the variation of free energy
in discrete categorical models which is
based on a demo from Ryan Smith and
Christopher white and Carl fursten's
paper
on uh unlike that big tutorial paper on
active inference so I re-implemented one
of the demos from that paper and now
that's also in the docs
um yeah so you can open all those demo
notebooks in collab and just step
through them um and they're really you
don't need to have even python installed
on your computer to use them you can
just open the links in collab and step
through the code and like build your own
active inference agents
so it's just useful for pedagogy that's
why I mentioned if you're just getting
started I would definitely recommend
going to the to the documentation
so yeah um thank you all for listening
and for uh letting giving me the chance
to to talk it was it was nice to be here
as always and I guess like yeah we
I I listed at the bottom for the next
live stream we can go through some of
the demo notebooks but we also could go
through them now if there's time maybe
we'll do discussion first and then just
see
there's time
awesome thanks yeah let's address some
questions from Daphne and Jacob I'll ask
some from the live chat and then perhaps
you could share
one or a few of the examples on the read
the docs and we could just look
structurally at what the anatomy and
physiology is of a notebook so first
Daphne or Jacob any
thoughts or questions
yeah yeah go for it
um I'm wondering on the on the Jacks
implementation
are there any requirements on defining
the generative process at all
or is it is it just about defining
the structure of the generative model
that we then fit to experimental data
and I guess this also relates to another
question I had in scaling these models
to State spaces or general processes
that we as modelers don't have the
Liberty to actually Define ourselves but
we want to
deploy and train
these agents in general processes that
are already out there like in an online
setting where you get categorical or
discrete
data coming in
yeah totally
um for so on the side of
that's a great question on the side of
um say I had a plan BP agent that had a
bunch of deep neural networks attached
to it and I wanted to train it uh on in
a deployed setting so it's like out
there you know let's say it's an agent
that's trading on the stock market or
something it's like placing
bets to buy like cryptocurrency let's
say
in that case in the same way to train a
deep neural network on that kind of data
you don't need to pass gradients through
the generative process which of course
you don't have access to you're trading
on the stock market so in that sense no
there's no requirements on passing
gradients or or writing up a generative
process that is also Auto differentiable
there is one case when you would want
that which is
often in the case of empirically
um fitting Pine DP models to data often
one thing that you want to do is you
have a bunch of like you basically have
a history of actions and observations of
a human participant you fit the model
the parameters of the pi VP agent that
best explain the observed actions of
your participant and you know the
observations because you're an
experimenter who like decided this
person is going to see the sequence of
observations so you can do all that
without having a differentiable
generative process or environment but
then there's something in in Bayesian
inference that's called like a posterior
predictive check where you say Okay
given my inference about the uh the
parameter of the pione P agent then I'd
like to roll out
the expected behavior of this agent
given the my best guess for what this
agent's parameters are so that's called
like a posterior predictive density
where you say given my posterior
um estimate about the agent's parameters
what would it look like in the future
under under these posterior parameters
and to do that in in using numpyro which
is the probabilistic inference framework
that uses Jax as a back end you would
want to have a generative process that
is also Auto differentiable
um but in that case I expect that
writing those generative processes would
be easy because that would be in the
case of fitting a human's Behavior to
experimental data where they're like in
a controlled task environment so if it
was the case of trying to fit someone's
parameters like the the value of their C
vector and they're performing that scene
construction task where they're sick
cutting around
you could write the generative process
because you as the experiment or
developed the psychophysical like task
that they're interacting with you could
write that also in Jax when you're doing
the modeling so that when you're doing
these posterior predictive checks you
know that that's also written in Jacks
and that you can compute those
quantities but in a deployed setting
you're not going to even be able to do
any kind of posterior predictive check
in the future because you don't know how
the environment actually works right
so you'd have to
you that that wouldn't even be something
that you tried to do in the first place
um but yeah so there's nothing
inherently stopping you from just as
long as the models are differentiable in
the same way they are with deep neural
networks there's nothing stopping you
from just throwing them into an
environment where you don't know how the
rules of the world work
yeah
the inexorable logic of natural
selection or free energy minimization or
just non-equilibrium systems
whether or not they know what's out
there
either it's going to work or it won't
and if it fails it fails and the
computational environment allows us to
exist in this kind of Gray Zone where
the computational agent might be quite
poorly adapted to a given deployed
setting but the computer program will
still run but of course we're interested
in cases where the computer program runs
and the agent is able to event some kind
of
meaningful or even useful Behavior
exactly like we could we could all
imagine very simple Prime DP models that
would do terribly in some tasks right
just like a dumb model that has two
hidden states that it believes just
stochastically switch between each other
and then you give it the task of
uh in making investments in like a 10
stock portfolio and of course its model
is not fit but the the promise of
applying big deep function approximators
to different ends of the Prime DP agent
means that hopefully you could then
learn a good generative model and then
still combine that with some lower
dimensional generative model up top that
can do all the nice inference and
planning with active inference but it
can deal with high dimensional or ugly
hard to tame observation and action
Spaces by using deep neural networks so
I think that's really the way to to just
in the same way deep learning has gotten
that to work in a lot of cases this is
the way to kind of do it with with prime
DP models as well
Daphne any remarks or I'll ask a few
from chat
um I don't really have any questions but
I do think that it is really fascinating
and like I think it's really exciting to
think about yeah like as you said like
learning the generative model of like an
agent learning its own generative model
given like some real world data to like
figure out like what is them and I guess
like in terms of what you were talking
about with like the function
approximations and numpyro and stuff is
that still like what like are you guys
still working like from that code base
and then finally convert those or have
it kind of started from scratch
yeah we we pretty much started from
scratch the pi DCM thing
I'm actually not sure what the like the
IP status of that is because we worked
on it as part of nested mine so I I
don't have access to that code anymore
but that was more implementing like
variational LaPlace in which you were we
worked on that together with variational
Applause injects which is the way that
you do gradient descent on free energy
when you're trying to do um inference
what we're doing now instead of that is
we're saying can you rewrite a pine DP
model
such that you can pass gradients through
it Jacks like accelerated gradients and
then use numpyro to do all kinds of
fitting routines not just variational
LaPlace but you could use mcmc you could
use like numpower just has a massive you
know library of different uh
probabilistic approximate Bayesian
inference techniques so you can kind of
throw the kitchen sink of numpyro
inference techniques at a prime DP model
so the challenge there is just rewriting
a prime DP model so you can Define like
a likelihood function that goes from
like the Palm DP parameters to the
observations which in this case would be
the actions of the agent and in order to
do that in a way so that can like play
friendly with Jax we just had to make
sure that all the interior functions of
the pine DP agent like the inference the
planning action selection all of that
was um written in Jacks so that you can
pass gradients through it when Computing
like likelihood gradients effectively
yeah that makes a lot of sense
yeah
all right I'll ask a few questions from
the live chat so first
most descriptions of active inference
across the literature are written in
terms of matrices but Pi mdp clearly
works with tensors
do you have a good reference for how the
operations are different when
generalizing the equations from matrices
to tensors
that's a really good point
um this is one of the things that
actually frustrated me a lot when I was
first learning about active inference
was I I noticed exactly what this person
asked is that a lot of the basic
operations
um
are written as if there's only single
dimensional hidden States and single
dimensional observations so everything
is like they said Matrix Vector products
and Matrix math but what we're really
doing is tensor multiplications and
tensor products so in terms of
references for how that works
um there's yeah so so essentially
there's nothing super qualitatively
different did these tensor operations
that we do in pione P are basically just
fancier ways of expressing
sums of matrix multiplication so there's
the mathematics of it is all still
standard linear algebra is just the way
we represent these high dimensional
matrices as tensors is just a more
efficient representation so
mathematically it's nothing too crazy
the way I learned about how that worked
was just by staring at functions in
Matlab for like a year until I just
figured it out but it wasn't easy and
there's definitely better options out
there now
um so um one reference off the bat I'll
recommend is is the appendix appendices
of
um Pi mdp uh the paper the archive paper
so that that like I think appendix a or
in all those appendices basically deal
with the full tensor factorized version
where it's not dealing with matrices but
we're actually indexing into higher
Dimensions another one which I think
um originally discusses the tensor
products and the tensor factorization is
in an appendix of I think active
inference curiosity and insight which is
where they first talked about like
novelty and parameter Information Gain
that's a paper
um I'm sorry I don't remember the year
it came out it's either 2017 or 2018 but
I know the paper title is called active
inference curiosity and insight and in
one of the appendices they actually do
the full tensor-based mathematics and
then finally another good reference is a
recent paper that was I think headed by
teofio Champion I'm just gonna try to
find it real quick because it's I don't
want to forget this
maybe I'll stop sharing my screen
did I stop okay it stopped
um
it's a really good reference that has
appendices
about
um doing tensor math
for active inference in particular
we also recently learned about the
branching time active inference which
speaks to some of those questions of
computational complexity and
and all
right yeah I should have mentioned that
that's like probably the most promising
approach to date about
the um uh to to finessing the
computational complexity of active
inference so yeah this this one is by
teofio Champions Mark gresh I guess
that's one of his advisors and Howard
Bowman his other advisor and that is
called multimodal and multi-factor
branching time active inference which I
just posted so I haven't read this
myself but I've heard from other people
like I think Alec chance told me that
the appendices are really good for the
tech the full tensor generalization of
active inference
all right awesome well I've added all of
those
um citations mentioned into the YouTube
live chat
awesome thank you I'm going to ask a
following question from Fausto
using a Jax backend makes it easy to
wrap
pymc3 apply MC3 around it EG to have pi
mdp as an operator to use in a pi MC3
model is there any plan to do this I ask
because there's a growing Bayesian
community in Python around Pi MC3
um that's really interesting I didn't
know actually that Prime G3 was also
had a Jacks back in so
um I'm I don't know to be to be honest
I'll start by saying that I don't know
because my introduction to like
probabilistic modeling in Python was
through DME Dimitri markovic who
basically sold me on numpyro numpyro is
the way of the future and I know numpyro
has a Jack's back end and I think
numpyro and Pi MC3 occupy a similar
place in that ecosystem of probabilistic
inference in Python
um I don't know how models are specified
in pi MC3 I am assuming it's not too
dissimilar from how it looks in numpyro
and because all the low-level back end
is now written in Jax I I can't promise
this but I would assume that you could
just write a pi MC3 model and the same
we wrote way we wrote a numpyro model
that wraps um Pi mdp functions but only
the pi MVP implementation injects so if
Pine Z3 only depends on Jax at the low
low level then yes it certainly can work
but um I don't know is there anyone else
here who has experience using pine G3
and might know
because I just don't know enough about
it
I used YMC a little bit but I think it
is like yeah as you said like quite
similar to numpyro I think that probably
you'd be able to
do the same things that you're doing
um with numpirers like integrating on
pyro at with pi MC3 as well
ah cool and so it's it's primary um back
end is Jax
is that
um I didn't actually do that um
I didn't know that either yeah
in comparison with the matrix
multiplication of Matlab
what makes you excited about the
probabilistic programming Direction and
all of these packages and approaches
that we're naming how does the
probabilistic programming differ from
just writing out the matrices and
calculating them on paper and why does
that have some promise for implementing
active inference models
um I think the biggest
advantage of the probabilistic
programming is not necessarily for
simulating active inference agents for
sure the Matrix multiplications are
sufficient having it in Jax makes it
much more scalable so you can use all
the vectorized operations to run like
tens of thousands of active inference
agents simultaneously because you have
these
highly optimized just-in-time compiled
functions and Jacks that allow you to it
just basically speeds things up an order
of magnitude but the probabilistic
programming angle is not as much for
simulating active inference processes as
it is for doing inference
or fitting models of active inference
agents to empirical data so say observe
an animal or a person doing something
now what we can do which we we can only
do an SPM but we can't do in Pine VP yet
until now is we can take a sequence of
someone's Behavior
and then infer the best
um parameters of an active inference
model that explain their behavior so
given how someone decided I can say oh
their a matrix must look like this or
their C Vector must have this um
Precision to it like you could infer
someone's risk sensitivity or uh their
risk aversion given their behavior and
the nice thing about being in
probabilistic programming languages is
there's so many different methods that
haven't been really well explored for
fitting active inference models in the
Matlab literature because almost
everyone there uses this um variational
Bayes approach where you basically
minimize free energy you use a gaussian
approximation for the posterior it's a
very specific
type of variational inference now that
it's in numpyro or perhaps Pi mt3 again
this will be very soon it's not fully
implemented yet we'll be able to throw
all different kinds of probabilistic
inference techniques that have their
different advantages and disadvantages
like a big thing in probabilistic
inferences is um mcmc Monte Carlo Markov
chain Monte Carlo inference it's
supposed to give less biased uh uh
posterior distributions like there's
advantages to using mcmc over
variational approaches to approximate
base and inference and one thing that I
haven't seen done which I would love to
see and a lot of people in the
computational Psychiatry Community have
have complained and told me what they'd
like to see is like a side-by-side
comparison of variational days to infer
Pi mdp parameters or Palm DP parameters
versus like mcmc approaches so once you
have everything in a probabilistic
program framework you can do side by
side comparisons between all the
different inference techniques that you
wouldn't necessarily have
um if you were limited by a language
where only at one or two or three
inference techniques are implemented so
it's basically just taking advantage of
all the work that people have worked on
numpyro have done in implementing all
these different kinds of uh inference
methods
yeah awesome and fausta followed up the
primary back end
uh for YMC is a Sarah but the new
version can use Jax I might get around
to writing the pi MC3 wrapper once the
Jax version of Pi mdp is stable it
sounds very doable
well that's awesome
if you see it as likely
and you have the affordance then just
minimize your free energy
and you won't be surprised when you do
it
absolutely that's great that's promising
nice
um Jacob or Daphne or I can ask another
question
the thing for me right now
well you mentioned message passing
several times in the context of Pi MGP
so what is message passing
and how was it used in pi mdp
it's a good question um so message
passing in general describes like a set
of algorithms that you can use to do an
exact or approximate Bayesian inference
um so oftentimes in in the to make it
very Concrete in the
in the context of doing Bayesian
inference about hidden States so what an
active inference agent will have to do
when they're faced with some observation
they'll have to combine messages like
one message corresponds to the message
the sensory information and then another
message corresponds to their prior
beliefs about the world and they use
some algorithm to combine those messages
to optimize a belief about the current
hidden state of the world so in pione P
we have a very naive kind of
computationally efficient doing way of
doing that which we just call naive or
vanilla fixed Point iteration which is
like the most simple message passing
scheme you can think of which is just
I'm actively filtering hidden States
using my priors from the past so I say
given where I was at the last time step
where should I be now given my B Matrix
and then I just essentially combined
that with my
incoming sensory message which is just
the observation passed through the
likelihood Matrix the a matrix and then
I just combine those two messages
together and that resulting thing is my
posterior distribution my posterior or
best belief about hidden States that's
like the simplest form of message
passing that has this very temporally
shallow
current evidence combined with prior to
form the new belief it has this very
kind of Bayesian flavor to it right
where the best posterior is just a
product of the likelihood and the prior
um
there's also more advanced message
passing techniques that are used when
your beliefs themselves are more
complicated so in the full
implementation of active inference
that's in the Matlab version agents
don't just have a belief about what the
current hidden state is they have a full
predictive and post-redictive kind of
um tensor or cube of beliefs about all
the hidden states in the future and all
the hidden states in the past further
condition on all the policies I will
potentially take or could have taken in
the past so you have this massive like
belief tensor uh that will stretching
into future and past hidden States and
uh further factorized by policy and when
you have that kind of belief that you
need to update you have to use more
sophisticated message passing techniques
one of which is called a marginal
message passing there's something called
variational message passing and all
these different message passing
techniques are just essentially
consistent in passing messages forwards
and backwards in time as well as across
different variable that characterize the
hidden state which we call Hidden State
factors
and and the message passing algorithms
are basically still
amount to combining sensory information
with prior beliefs but they just have
kind of more complicated trajectories
through the space of beliefs in the
future in the past there's I'm there's
people who can explain this much better
than me I've implemented some of these
in pi mdp but I would refer people to
there's a really nice um paper
I think you may have retweeted it the
other day Jacob it's about
um
it's called mean field
oh yeah
um the paper comparing the mean field
and that they approximation and the best
air approximation neuronal message
passing using mean Fields Bethy and
marginal approximation
par Markovich kibel and friston 2019
um it's a paper that a few of us have
been walking through looking at how the
different free energy functionals look
different under different approximations
and it'll probably be a focal paper in
2023 for us to really dive into
because a lot of these um
vintage let's say 2011 to 2019 papers
now packages and development directions
such as Pi mdp
are facilitating
[Music]
these methods to be actually used and
there's a huge wealth
of conceptual possibility it proposed
heuristics exciting use cases
relevant other kinds of connections and
um
as you brought up earlier
it was very Matlab bounds to bring those
kinds of connections into the last mile
and then especially
the more granular or modular
developments
were
Under the Umbrella of the SPM vbx
which prevented them from being
meaningfully
shared
in a true distributed open science or
decentralized science way
and so that's why of course we've been
so excited to work with and build on
Prime DP and learn about it more because
this is exactly the kind of
composability of active inference agents
and their different implementations that
is going to be able to be worked on in a
massively distributed way somebody might
specify a really interesting a matrix
somebody else might specify an
interesting B somebody else is going to
link those together into a new kind of
agent
someone else can implement it
differently and so it brings like a
natural it kind of factorizes
the process of developing these
algorithms which previously were almost
always
either fully Matlab
or and or bespoke
and very custom
and fit for a given paper
but not necessarily adaptable along the
relevant axes
that one would want to use for a modern
especially pythonic setting
totally I can agree more I mean that's a
great way of thinking about it too is
like I'm making modular flexible code
that exists in the ecosystem of other
packages you're essentially
factorizing the collective Minds
representation of the task at hand or
then different parts of that
representation can be worked on without
having to pass messages or take into
account what's going on across the
entire network of distributed workers so
like someone can write their own you
know even better message passing
algorithm and then just slot it in to
use with pi MVP without having had to
learn about how every little facet of
prime DP works you know so yeah that's a
really important I think thing about
just open science and modular software
development
nice well in our closing minutes of
course Jacob or Daphne any remarks or
questions and also any appetizer what
kind of models are people excited about
and or what might mean we see in the
following live stream which will be in
January 2023
model stream 7.2
um I would just say that I think that
the notebooks are really really useful
so like it's a really great resource for
people who
um are trying to build and model and
understand like what's going on under
the native IMDb and I think that it
would be really cool to have an
extension to those notebooks that also
talks about
learning the duration parameters for the
A and B matrices I think that that would
be really really cool
and thank you so much Connor you wanted
to talk
yeah thank you for coming that's a
really good point and this is something
that Daniel also said
um earlier in the email is that updating
A and B is like it's very very under
documented right now
and I think that would be because that
is a form of learning the generative
model
um that right now we don't it's not the
most sophisticated way you still have a
fixed number of rows and columns so you
make some assumptions but that is like a
flexible way when the agents are
themselves learning the b and a matrices
so
um yeah we should definitely maybe that
can actually be a
I I can just add that into the notebook
that I was planning on
showing this like a kind of epistemic
two-armed Bandit task we can just add in
some A or B learning to that and just
show how that works
um I would make a new notebook that uses
that
cool eventually for the textbook
and for every paper
it would be amazing to be able to see
the code
the analytical representation a
graphical representation and different
natural language representations
because they're all formally uh formally
connected and they could all be rendered
as such and that would really
one might expect increase the
accessibility and rigor of a model
and help us compose and connect across
different domains and just welcome and
recognize many different kinds of
learning and modeling
absolutely
jakov any
thoughts or questions
um no questions at this point but uh
also just thanks a lot for the awesome
presentation and I'm really excited
about all the emerging
um
Integrations and use cases that will
that will undoubtedly uh spring up we've
been uh we started exploring uh numpyro
as well and kind of discussing how
um that can be used for scalable active
inference models and I'm really excited
how primevp will
um
interoperate with all of these different
Integrations and it will be very
um exciting to use
thank you
Connor any penultimate words
um I guess maybe just in in the spirit
of what you were saying I can just show
a skeleton of what we could go through
next time oh great all right we see it
um yeah is that is that okay it looks
great looks great
so
yeah basically this is a collab notebook
so I encourage anyone to go to the
um Pine DP tutorial website and each of
the notebooks like Daphne was saying
they had their I'm pretty useful and
they have collab links associated with
them
um and you can just open the link and
then explore this one I think is part of
the agent
API yeah this is the same one except I
showed this one recently at the course
on computational Psychiatry so I've
updated a little bit
so I can share this with
um you Daniel and then you could either
put on the Discord or wherever this
one's a little bit more updated but the
basic one here will still
that you can access here will still show
the same thing
but um in any case the thing is you just
open up collab you need a Google account
that's the one limitation to use these
um you can install locally infra
actively Dash piondp
uh import numpy matplotlib there's just
some imports here and then this whole
this the spirit of this notebook is
essentially just going through all the
steps in setting up the generative model
so creating your hidden State factors
that's something we didn't really talk
about is factorized representations in
the context of Pi mdp
um
building the B array which
not only has
um like you can just do it yourself but
there's also these hidden cells with
solutions to each of these things and
then the main brunt of this notebook
before running active inference is just
stepping through and actually
initializing
um the entries of the a b c and d arrays
and next time I have some slides to go
along with this so we can basically go
between the slides and
the actual code
same thing with the a array so you like
have uh some representation of what you
want the a matrix to look like and then
you go into the code and actually build
it out and you do that sequentially for
each of the components of the generative
model
um
and you're plotting them along the way
so you can see what it looks like after
you've built it and then we actually
uh we actually Implement after you've
built the general model then you
actually plug it in to an active
inference agent
so this this the first stuff is building
a factorized a and b for a generic
um General that I think is just a more
sophisticated grid world but then we
actually that's kind of the introductory
task and then we go in and we actually
build the A's and B's and c's for this
epistemic two-armed banded task which is
basically just like a teammates
um
and then you uh build that out you know
you're writing in all the little sub
matrices of your a matrix
that's why there's so many cells like I
said it's like that's the longest part
it's actually building things out
[Music]
um
the C Vector basically the reward
function which has Daphne was saying
earlier you're actually encoding in
terms of relative log probabilities
and then finally you basically do those
those steps that we discussed during the
presentation you just plug all your
painstakingly generated A's and B's
hopefully not too painstaking into your
agent class you generate the two armed
Bandit the epistemic to arm bandit uh
environment which is just the rules
about how the world Works given the
agent's actions and then you actually
run this active inference Loop which is
as we discussed just effectively running
a loop over time doing hidden State
influence policy inference action
sampling and then stepping the
environment to get the new observation
and then at the end I've just written
this like helper function that can
basically plot the history of choices
and beliefs
um so then you at the very end this is
like the more a fun experimental part
you can mess with the parameters of the
uh environment and also the parameters
of the agent's model
and then start seeing how that changes
behavior
um just by kind of iteratively running
active inference simulations and
plotting the resulting Choice behavior
and history of beliefs
so that's the general that's a little
preview I guess of what we can do and we
can also have a little sub module in
here we're actually letting the agents
update their beliefs about the a or the
B Matrix which could be cool
awesome looks really exciting and on a
final SPM note
in the SPM textbook and in experiments
sometimes there are these incredible
grayscale matrices that summarize like
multiple experimental factors across 100
participants and uh so it's really
interesting to see how
you show with also that black and white
or grayscale Matrix representation
and how that provides a visual feel
for some of these topics that we've been
discussing it and of course
the representation is
formally linked with the Matrix but
sometimes just saying well you have two
options and there's ten states in the
world and the likelihoods look like this
instead of seeing that as like a
spreadsheet with numbers seeing them
in the grayscale
provides kind of a feel
and it looks really nice and so it looks
like an awesome
session we'll have for DOT two
yeah totally that's interesting that you
bring that up like that's something I've
just always been doing and I think it's
very much because I
learned all of that from Reading those
active inference and SPM papers
um so I very much just kind of borrowed
that visualization technique from them
um and I kind of took it for granted but
yeah it is interesting it's clearly not
the only way to go but I always just
found it very intuitive to think of
probability you just kind of can color
it use colors because the numbers are
too specific it's the color the
grayscale that visual aspect really like
kind of just shows this thing is more
likely than this thing
yeah yep
cool all right well
Daphne and Connor thanks a lot for this
awesome session and
we'll see you in a little bit more than
a month for the dot two
great thanks so much Daniel and thank
you everyone
peace
take care bye thanks everyone